<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Newes from Spaine A relation of the death of Don Rodrigo Calderon, marques of seven churches, &amp;c. Faithfully translated according to the Spanish copy printed at Madrid. By Fernando Manojo. From the court.</title>
            <author>Manojo de la Corte, Fernando.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 32 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06821</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17258</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105407</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841135</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841135</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5695</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06821)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5695)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 580:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Newes from Spaine A relation of the death of Don Rodrigo Calderon, marques of seven churches, &amp;c. Faithfully translated according to the Spanish copy printed at Madrid. By Fernando Manojo. From the court.</title>
                  <author>Manojo de la Corte, Fernando.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[20] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>With licence, by the widdow of Fernando Correa de Montenegro],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at Madrid :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴(-A1) B-C⁴(-C4).</note>
                  <note>Slight print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Calderón, Rodrigo, d. 1621.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:5695:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5695:1"/>
            <p>Newes from Spaine. A RELATION OF THE DEATH OF DON RODRIGO CALDERON, MARQVES OF SEVEN Churches, &amp;c. Faithfully tranſlated according to the Spaniſh Copy Printed at MADRID. By Fernando Manojo. From the Court. 1622.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:5695:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5695:2"/>
            <head>Newes from Spaine.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>ON RODERIGO CALDERON was the ſonne of <hi>Franciſco Calderon,</hi> who being a Souldier in Flanders, begot him of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria de Sandalin</hi> a German woman. He was made legitimate many yeeres after by the marriage of his Parents, and borne in Antwerp, amidſt the wants of Warre and militarie Misfortunes. Being a Child of few moneths old, he was let downe the Citie wall (an angrie preſage of what was to ſucceede) to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoide the danger of a ſacke, without receiuing any hurt but feare. His Father (now a Widdower) borne at Valliadolid, of honeſt Parentage, with ſome Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance, brought him thither, and ſeeing him growne vp, and not beloued by a Mother in law, whom hee had made his ſecond Wife, thinking how to ſetle him in ſome courſe to liue; placed him firſt as Page with the Vice-chancelor of Arragon, and after with the Marques of <hi>Denia, Don Franciſco Gomez de Sandoual y Rojas,</hi> now Duke of Lerma, who then ſate at the ſterne of this Monarchie, and was ſtyled the Fauorite of King <hi>Philip</hi> the Third, now with God. <hi>Don Roderigo</hi> ſhot vp ſo faſt, vnder the ſhadow of his Maſters Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and trenched ſo deepe into his fauour, that hee got to be a Groome of the Bed-chamber: And, after <hi>Don Pedro Franqueza,</hi> Earle of Villa-longa, hee was made Secretarie of Eſtate, and onely managed the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of diuers; ſo that Expedition in the great affaires of <hi>Iuſtice</hi> and <hi>Reward</hi> paſt through his hands. He was Actiue and Intelligent, of a comely Preſence, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what haughtie toward Suiters (whoſe companie then
<pb facs="tcp:5695:3"/> he wanted not) but punctuall, obſequious, and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full where he meant to pleaſe. He married with <hi>Dona Ynas de Vergas,</hi> Lady of <hi>Oliua;</hi> which Title hee left after to his eldeſt Sonne <hi>Don Franciſco Calderon.</hi> His Father (an honeſt man) ſought not to riſe, but wiſely noting the inclination of his Sonne, diſſwaded him ſometimes from it, whereat taking diſlike, blowne vp with the winde of Ambition, he forgot ſomewhat his naturall duetie, (deſirous to linke himſelfe to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily of a great Lord of theſe Kingdomes, who was Gouernour in Flanders where he was borne) yet hee aduanced his Father (a Widdower now the ſecond time) to bee a Knight of Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> and <hi>Alcayde</hi> of <hi>Conſuegra:</hi> after of Saint <hi>Iames,</hi> where he was Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of the Order, and had the beſt <hi>Encomienda</hi> in Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragon; in which place, like a Chriſtian wiſe man, he bounded the limits of his fortune. The trumpe of Fame ſounded farre the name of <hi>Don Rodrigo,</hi> and his great fauour with the Duke, and ſtrooke in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment. Hence pride of heart entring, made him treat preſumptuouſly with diuers, and Power and Greatneſſe laid open vnto him occaſions of Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Briberie, from whence grew his exceſſiue wealth. Ill Report publiſhed his great faults ſo broad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that hee ſought to ſhelter himſelfe vnder the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of his Maieſties Pardon (gotten indirectly as was ſaid) by which hee receiued plenarie Abſolution for all was paſt. But by occaſion of the Duke of Ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maes retreat from Court to his owne Houſe, his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes were againe divulged, with a common imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Deaths, Falſifications, Witchcrafts and Bribe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. The particulars were theſe. He was accuſed by the Atturney Generall, culpable of the death of our
<pb facs="tcp:5695:3"/> Queene, Lady <hi>Margaret</hi> of Auſtria, who is with God: but becauſe the proofes were not pregnant, he was of that acquitted, as alſo for the deaths of <hi>Alonſo de Cara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vajal,</hi> Father <hi>Chriſtopher Suarez</hi> a Ieſuite, <hi>Pedro Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uallero,</hi> and <hi>Pedro de Camino.</hi> But for the impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and death of <hi>Auguſtine de Auila</hi> (an <hi>Alguazil</hi> of this Court) and circumſtances thereof; and the aſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinate committed on the perſon of <hi>Franciſco de Xuara,</hi> by the Sergeant <hi>Iohn de Guſman</hi> at his procurement, and for hauing vnduely obtayned the Pardon of his Maieſtie deceaſſed, for his ſaid offences; hee was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudged to die. He had notice thereof from <hi>Lazaro de los Rios, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>HIs Titles, Offices, and Commodities, were theſe, which follow. He was Marques of ſeuen Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, Earle of <hi>Oliua, Comendador</hi> of <hi>Ocana,</hi> Knight of the Order of Saint <hi>Iames,</hi> Captaine of the German Guard, Treaſurer of the Houſe of Arragon, Regiſter of the Chancerie of Valladolid, Steward of the works of the ſaid Citie, Chiefe <hi>Alguazil</hi> of the ſaid Citie and Chancerie, and <hi>Alcayde</hi> of the Kings priſon. He had two Regencies there, and the firſt voyce and place in Court. He was chiefe Poſt-maſter of that Citie. He had a <hi>Marauedi</hi> for euery Bull of the <hi>Cruzada</hi> that was imprinted in Valladolid, of the Kings gift, which came to aboue ſixe thouſand Duckats of rent. He had alwaies a Chamber of allowance in the Play-houſes of Valladolid, as alſo in the Corral of Madrid. He was <hi>Regidor</hi> of <hi>Soria,</hi> and had a voyce in Court. Hee had two Regencies in the Citie of Placentia, and a voyce in Court. He was depoſitarie Generall in the ſaid Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and had a voyce in Court. He was Regiſter of the
<pb facs="tcp:5695:4"/> Court of the ſaid Citie. He had the Patronage of the Monaſterie of <hi>Porta Coali</hi> in Valladolid. The Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage of the Riall Chappell of the Monaſterie of the <hi>Mercedes</hi> of Madrid. His houſe-hold ſtuffe was va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lued at foure hundred thouſand Duckats. He had halfe of the mother of Pearle brought from the Eaſt Indies, contayning thirtie <hi>Quintals</hi> of ſhells, which among the Negroes paſſeth currant for Bullion. Hee had the Impoſt of Braſil wood that came from Lisbone, worth twelue thouſand Duckats a yeere. He had a Graunt, that none without his leaue, could barter for Milſtones and Whetſtones as Barbers vſe, which come from for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine Parts, to ſend them to the Eaſt Indies; this was worth to him many Duckats.</p>
               <p>It is verified for certaine, that he receiued yeerly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue two hundred thouſand Duckats of rent. To par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularize all his wealth, would aske along time.</p>
               <p>His Father, his two Sonnes, two Daughters, and his Wife, went from Madrid two dayes before hee died, hauing much bewayled his fall, and wrought much for his deliuerie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>The Executioner lead his Mule, and (according to the cuſtome of Spaine) made Proclamation. This is the iuſtice which the King our Soueraigne Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth to be done on this Man, for hauing treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly killed a man, committing an aſſaſinate, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing guil tie of the death of another, with other offences as appeareth by his Iudgement: wherefore he is to be beheaded, and be an example, that others that ſhal doe the like, may haue the like.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="relation">
            <pb facs="tcp:5695:4"/>
            <head>A Relation of the death of <hi>Don Rodrigo Calderon,</hi> Marques of ſeuen Churches, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Stand in doubt to write what will ſeeme ſtrange to many, and my Relation be taxed as too ſhort, by thoſe which ſaw it acted, and by others, which ſaw it not, too affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionate: but the ſynceritie of my intent is grounded on the meane, taken from a particular Confeſſion which diſcouereth the greatneſſe of the Action, and rareneſſe of the Caſe. <hi>Don Rodrigo Calderon,</hi> late Marques of ſeuen Churches, Earle of <hi>Oliua,</hi> Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne of the German Guard, a Knight of the Order of Saint <hi>Iames,</hi> and <hi>Comendador</hi> of <hi>Ocana,</hi> being impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned in his owne houſe with a ſtrong Guard, hauing but the vſe of one onely Chamber with little light; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his Cauſe had beene in diſcuſſing two yeeres and a halfe, had ſentence of death giuen againſt him, by the Lords of the Aſſembly, <hi>Don Franciſco de Contreras</hi> (now moſt worthy Preſident of Caſtile) <hi>Luis de Salze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do,</hi> and <hi>Don Diego del Corral.</hi> He had notice thereof by <hi>Lazaro de los Rios,</hi> a Regiſter of the Proceſſe, the fourteenth of Iuly 1621. To which he made anſwer, that he heard it. Then turning to a Crucifixe, he ſaid; <hi>God be bleſſed, whoſe will be in me fulfilled:</hi> which was like ſome other of his actions, both before and after (which, to be ſhort, I let paſſe in ſilence) grounded on a vertuous Spirit, wholly exerciſed in ſpirituall books of deuotion, and full of Religion and Chriſtian cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage. From that time, vntill his death, which was three moneths after, hee neuer was vnclothed, nor came in bed. There was a Pallet by his bed ſide, with
<pb facs="tcp:5695:5"/> a leather couerlet, on which in the night hee reſted a little, ſpending the moſt part of it in mentall Prayer, wherein he much profited by reading a Booke of the holy Mother <hi>Tereſa</hi> of IESVS, to which hee was much affected, ſo that hee could repeate by memorie whole Pages thereof: as alſo out of a Booke of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, compoſed by Father <hi>Molina;</hi> and in ſpirituall Conferences had with the Religious, he cited to them theſe Books, or others ſuch like. Hee daily read the liues of Saints in <hi>Flos Sanctorum,</hi> perſwaded there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto by Mother <hi>Tereſa</hi> and Father <hi>Molina,</hi> of whom (as he ſaid) he learned it. He made a generall Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion with Humilitie and Contrition, accompanied with many teares of tenderneſſe, witneſſing the good preparation of his mind, for what was to come; but to declare particulars, would make rather a Booke then a briefe Relation.</p>
            <p>And I heard Friar <hi>Gabriel</hi> his Confeſſor ſay, who is Procurator Generall of the diſcalced Carmelites (a religious perſon of venerable fame) that during thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie yeeres ſpace, wherein he had beene a Phyſician for Soules, hee neuer experienced the like: for neither when the ſentence of death was notified vnto him, or vpon any diſcomfort did he change countenance, or ſhed teare; but when he remembred his ſinnes, they fell like ſhowres. O force of diuine loue! which doth ſoften hearts not ſhaken with aduerſitie, from whence proceedeth their Fortitude and Humilitie. Hee had conference with diuers Religious, and particularly with Friar <hi>Gregorie de Pedros,</hi> a Preacher to his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, whoſe great parts of learning and eloquence are alreadie blazond by fame, and need no report of mine. To him and his Confeſſor hee vnfolded his Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb facs="tcp:5695:5"/> with Securitie and Satisfaction, not regarding Honour, or any other pretext, hauing ſo reſigned vp his will to God, and his obedience to his Confeſſor. That humane feares wrought litle in him, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoluing ſpeedily what difficulties they propoſed. How excellent hee was in this, his death will beare witneſſe. He petitioned an appeale from his Iudgement, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as his Counſell aduiſed him: but his diligence in procuring his defence, neuer diuerted his minde from the conſideration of his death, nor made him omit the exerciſes of a vertuous life. The Iudges did not admit his Appeale, but inſiſted on the execution of the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence: whereof he hauing notice the firſt of October, anſwered; <hi>I heare it,</hi> and turning to a Crucifixe, ſaid: <hi>God be bleſſed, whoſe will be in me fulfilled.</hi> No impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient word was euer heard fall from him, for as his Soule grew daily nearer Heauen, ſo ſhewed hee moſt courage in moſt diſcomfort, not being ſenſible of earthly loſſes, but falling out of loue with them, the ioy of his Spirit flew a higher pitch, then the diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of this World did reach vnto, ſo that on the day of his death (had not his Confeſſor hindred it) hee would haue proclaymed his ſinnes in the ſtreet, as hee oft ſought to doe in priſon, if he had beene permitted. His Appeale being not admitted, and the Iudgement confirmed; on Tueſday at midnight, Friar <hi>Pedro de la Concepcion,</hi> went to him with this newes, in place of his Confeſſor, who then was not well, who told him hee was to receiue his <hi>Viaticum</hi> on Wedneſday. Hee found him quiet at his prayers, which hee vſed much, and receiued in them particular fauours from God. He demanded of him wherefore he came: hee anſwered, to ſpend the night with you. Falling to diſcourſe of
<pb facs="tcp:5695:6"/> the miſeries of this life, and of the happineſſe of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that is without end, hauing fit time, hee ſaid to him: Who would not with a good will, exchange a life temporall for an eternall? To which he anſwered. Alas, Father, would I had not this one, but a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand liues to loſe for Gods ſake: then (replied the Friar) hee will come to you to morrow, and giue you the Pledge of his Grace, to receiue hereafter the Crowne of his Glorie. He then preſently conceiuing wherefore he ſaid ſo; kneeled downe before a Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixe, and with great zeale of deuotion, ſaid thrice: <hi>Thy will be done, O Lord</hi> (vſing this reſignation of mind in all his tribulations.) Then riſing vp, hee ſaid, I haue ſomething to doe; and going behind the bed, he put on a ſhirt of haire, and a croſſe with ſharpe pricks of ſteele, which he ware about his necke, hauing (for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to his Confeſſor) put them off the day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, to mitigate his continuall penance, making his vertues more ſecure, by the ſecrecie wherewith hee practized them. This hee did on dayes of faſting, which was weekly, Wedneſday, Friday, and Sater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, and in thoſe of abſtinence, not taſting any thing that might pleaſe him, yet ſo warily that thoſe which attended him obſerued it not. The reſt of the night, he ſpent in ſpirituall Exerciſes. And when the Friar propounded to him, how God rewarded thoſe that take benefit by afflictions, offering them in imitation of his moſt painefull Paſſion: hee anſwered. I pray God, Father, my ſinnes cauſe mee not to loſe ſo great Happineſſe; although, I aſſure you, I feele ſuch com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort now, that if it would not ſeeme lightneſſe in mee, I could laugh. Neither was his feare vnlike his hope;
<pb facs="tcp:5695:6"/> affections which tyed him alike to God; humilitie and acknowledgement of his owne miſerie, accompanied the one; and truſt in Gods Mercy and Power, the other. On Wedneſday morning, he diſpoſed the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of his Soule by direction of his Confeſſor, and of Friar <hi>Gregorie de Pedroſa,</hi> whoſe aſſiſtance was of great comfort and profit to him. Then he went into the Chappell, wearing the white mantle of his Order, where his Confeſſor ſaid Maſſe, and he Receiued, with great Faith and Loue of God: at which time, with a Spirit full of zeale, he ſaid: <hi>O Lord, ſince thou commeſt to me to day, let me come to thee to morrow;</hi> and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to thoſe wordes of conſolation: <hi>In manus tuas Domine commendo Spiritum meum:</hi> hee added, <hi>Vitam &amp; honorem meum.</hi> The Maſſe being ended where he Rcceiued, hee heard other foure, with ſuch tranquili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and deuotion, that he neuer ſighed nor lamented, being thereat out of modeſtie aſhamed, leſt his deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhould bee therefore accounted rather vaine-glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, then vertuous: in this hee excelled, as his priuate Almes, giuen in the time of his better for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, beare witneſſe; and the Religious, by whoſe hands they paſſed, can affirme. The Chappell, in which lyeth the body of the holy Mother <hi>Tereſa</hi> of IESVS, in the Church of the Diſcalced Carmelites at Madrid, was part of his Almes, which hee deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to make more ſumptuous, if his Order had per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted. Hee alſo built the Heremitage in the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert <hi>de Batuccas,</hi> and cauſed two Maſſes to bee daily ſaid in that which is neare to Peſtrana. Hee ſaid the Office of our Lady, and for the Soules departed, hauing continued it many yeeres. He was Confeſſed,
<pb facs="tcp:5695:7"/> and receiued in the Paſcall Feaſts, our Ladies, and the Apoſtles, and examined daily his conſcience: which he vſed for theſe foure or fiue yeeres laſt paſt, to doe twice a day. Hee had thrice made his generall Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion before this laſt, which he ended on Saint <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thewes</hi> Eue, and Receiued the next day. In the priſon he was confeſſed twice or thrice a weeke, after he might with leaue doe it. Hee paſſed the euening with his Confeſſor, and with Friar <hi>Gregorie de Pedroſa,</hi> in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall queſtions, ſo high, that it appeared, God was his Tutor, and the Schoole the Priſon, as he ſaid. In his Spirituall conference, theſe words eſcaped him: <hi>I wiſh I could giue a thouſand liues for mine Enemies.</hi> His Confeſſor checked him for calling them Enemies; whereat recalling himſelfe, hee humbly demanded how hee ſhould name them? His Confeſſor told him, hee ſhould make that Recognition for thoſe which ſought to hurt him, if any ſuch were. He much eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med this aduiſe, and fulfilled it. This night, Father <hi>Iohn de la Madre de Dios,</hi> companion to his Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor, brought him a Memoriall of Bequeſts from the Religious of his Order, which were Prayers and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtings. Hee was greatly comforted therewith, and humbly anſwered, that he hoped to ſee himſelfe with God, and to beſeech his diuine Maieſtie to reward their great charitie. Giuing diſcreet ſatisfaction vnto all, and not leauing any thing by his neare approach to death vnperformed, that belonged to curteſie and vrbanitie, or vertuous policy. So that when ſome came to demand of him debts, no iuſt cauſe moouing them: he anſwered, If his eſtate were in himſelfe, hee could diſpoſe thereof as hee liked; but being now in
<pb facs="tcp:5695:7"/> his Maieſtie, he ſtood obliged to defend it, and make no declaration in preiudice of the true Owner, for thoſe that vniuſtly ſought to haue it. Talking with Father <hi>Iohn de la Madre de Dios,</hi> he ſaid: My Father, Wife, Children, Eſtate and Honour, is taken from me, as to morrow ſhall bee my Life; but that which onely grieueth mee, is, that I haue no more to loſe for Gods ſake; the memory of the loſſe of theſe things did not trouble him, but the deſire that his death might giue example to others ſo to liue, as to ſaue their Soules. O generous condition of a zealous Soule! All loue ſeemed too little, compared with the greatneſſe of the Obiect; and light encreaſing accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to loue, diſcerned more clearely the vnlimited diſtance betweene humane power, and diuine Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potency. Being late in the night, hee was importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the Religious there preſent, to lye downe on his Pallet, which he did, holding a Crucifixe, and by him the Picture of the holy Mother <hi>Tereſa</hi> of IESVS; there he repoſed a while, ouercome rather with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation then ſleepe. Hee demanded of Friar <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dro de la Concepcion,</hi> if hee ſhould receiue Extreame Vnction: who anſwered, That the Church vſed not to giue it to thoſe that dyed ſo. Them (ſaid he) ſince I cannot receiue this Sacrament, doe me the curteſie, to teach mee the Ceremonies thereof, to know them before I dye. The Friar tooke a Manual, and ſaid the Prayers, Letanies, and Ceremonies, omitting the ſubſtance of the Sacrament. He gaue eare to all with humble attention and deuotion, not ſhunning, but ſeeking earneſtly to prepare himſelfe to dye, in the well performing whereof, he placed his greateſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe.
<pb facs="tcp:5695:8"/> Then hee continued in mentall Prayer, from fiue a clocke vntill ſixe in the morning, with admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable recollection, for the which, afterward hee infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely thanked God. Here let Contemplatiues, prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized in prayer, conſider the diuine Fauours ſhewed by this Repoſe, to a man that had the ſword laid to his throat, whoſe threed of Life was euen ſpunne, the repreſentation of Death ſecuring the attention of his Spirit, who being vnloaded from the weight of this mortality, was vnited to its euerlaſting Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: a thing ſo deſired by thoſe that treate with God, and onely effected by Death, and wiſhed of him, as the meane to obtayne ſo glorious an End. That mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning hee put off his haire ſhirt before his Confeſſor, modeſtly preuenting the publique inconuenience which might enſue, by what hee deſired to haue ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret. Then kneeling downe before diuers graue Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious perſons, he read a proteſtation of Faith, which himſelfe had made. In it was contayned, a quinteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of inward zeale, vttered in wordes, ſo feeling and ſignificant, that it cauſed both admiration and confuſion. <hi>Don Pedro Fernandez de Manſilla,</hi> an <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayde</hi> of the Court, came to take his leaue of him, whom he met halfe way, with a behauiour and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of ſuch ſerenitie, that it paralleld not with his preſent eſtate. <hi>Don Pedro</hi> deſired him to commaund him ſome ſeruice, to which hee anſwered, That ſince hee gaue him leaue ſo to doe, hee beſought him for a quick diſpatch in his Wife and Childrens buſineſſe (which was a ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>te for Land with his Maieſtie, that depended before <hi>Don Pedro de Manſilla</hi>) to this hee gaue him a courteous anſwere. Thoſe that then were
<pb facs="tcp:5695:8"/> preſent, began to ſhead teares, and ſigh, ſeeing a cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage ſo vndaunted, and a preſence ſo venerable. Hee ſeeing himſelfe to bee the Cauſe of their woe, comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them, ſaying: Sirs, it is no time to lament, but to reioyce, ſince I am going to doe the <hi>Will of God.</hi> Theſe wordes gaue cauſe of comfort to pious minds, by diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couering the good eſtate of his Soule and great Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianitie. Then he went into the Chappell in a Cloke, and vpon it the habite of Saint <hi>Iames,</hi> where he heard many Maſſes. He intreated the Carmelite that ſaid it, to put his Soule together with the Hoſt into the Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice. This was to follow the example of the holy Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Tereſa</hi> of IESVS, who on a Palme Sunday ſaid the like. This wrought ſo good effect, that hee was comforted both in Soule and Body, and incouraged to ſuffer. He gaue his Roſarie to a religious man of the Order of Saint <hi>Hierome,</hi> for accounting himſelfe as dead, he prepared for his owne <hi>Dirge.</hi> Thus hee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued, performing many acts of Contrition, in fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent prayer, vntill the time of execution. At eleuen, Friar <hi>Gregorie de Pedroſa</hi> came vnto him, and ſaid: Sir, now let vs goe, for God calleth vs. He preſently an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered; <hi>Let vs goe.</hi> When they put off the Cloke of his Order, there came one and put a Hood ouer his ſhort Coate, from which and from his doublet he had the night before, cut the necke, and the ſtrings from his band, in place whereof he had put a button, to come more ready to his laſt End, knowing hee was made a ſacrifice to God, who diſpoſed the meanes to make his death more eaſie, which hee receiued rather with Loue then Feare. When hee went out of the Chappell, he told his Confeſſor, he felt himſelfe very
<pb facs="tcp:5695:9"/> weake both in Soule and Body: who anſwered him; Truſt in God, and pray to him for ſtrength, and hee will not deny it you at this time. Comming to the ſtayres, God gaue him courage, that it now ſeemed not difficult to him to go in the ſtreets, as it was wont; ſo other things, which in his imagination appeared vnpoſſible, comming to act them, by Gods aſſiſtance, were become very fezible. Comming downe the ſtayres, and ſeeing a Mule ready for him, hee ſaid: What, a Mule? Nay, I ought rather to be dragged in a basket; practizing ſtill more pure Acts of Humilitie and contempt of the World, and deſiring the moſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gracefull death. He rode on the Mule without feare, ſquaring all his actions to the rules of Modeſty, and neceſſity without oſtentation. Then he toeke a Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifixe which he imbraced ſo affectuouſly, that it made great impreſſion in the beholders. Going on, the people cryed: God pardon, and giue you ſtrength: to whom he anſwered, <hi>Amen; God reward you.</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to the Market place of Saint <hi>Dominick,</hi> and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Prayers and Cryes of the people, he lifted vp his eyes, and ſaid: <hi>Lord, ſince they all aske my Pardon, Pardon me, I beſeech thee.</hi> When he came to the <hi>Smiths</hi> little ſtreet, he ſaid to his Confeſſor: Father, this is rather a triumph, then a carrying the Croſſe of Chriſt, who was blaſphemed, and I am prayed for. Pray, Father, that the ioy I now feele, bee not a reward for that little I haue ſuffered for his ſake. I dare not weigh theſe wordes in the ballance of my Reaſon. Let vs leaue ſomething in ſilence, ſince his valour and ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, will ſooner be ſearched into by a zealous affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, then vttered by an eloquent tongue. He fixed his
<pb facs="tcp:5695:9"/> eyes, with a graue aſpect vpon a Crucifixe there pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, teſtifying therby the recollection of his thoughts. In his contemplation he remembered the ſpirituall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement, giuen him by the Religious which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied him, diuinely diſcourſing on the Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to come. Being come to the place of Execution, with a conſtant Countenance, hee alighted from his Mule, and without any helpe, went vp the Scaffold. He beheld without feare the Sword and Blocke. Set his Hood right, and ſaid to the Religious: <hi>Let me reſt here awhile.</hi> His Confeſſor, and Friar <hi>Gregorie de Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>droſa,</hi> ſate downe about him, with the reſt of the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, in number twelue, no perſon, but what was needfull, being ſuffered to enter. They kneeled downe to pray for his Soule. He read diuers Iaculatory pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, with ſuch reſignation and attention, that his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructors ſtood aſtoniſhed. After a good while he roſe, and told his Confeſſor, he felt himſelfe comforted, to ſee that God wrought in him his will, ſaying, it was fit to thanke him therefore, and bee confeſſed before death, and abſolued by the Bull of Faith in Baptiſme, with a proteſtation thereof. <note place="margin">Hee did the like at the time of his confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</note> Hee was confeſſed, and receiuing abſolution, he fell on the ground and kiſſed the feete of his Confeſſor. Being commanded to riſe, hee went to his Chaire, not to dye, but to triumph, with ſuch courage, humilitie, and magnanimitie, that all were filled with pietie and admiration. A part of his Hood he caſt behind the chaire, and prayed whilſt the Executioner made all things readie. Then he calld him, imbraced him, and ſpake to him moſt louingly. Hee proceeded ſo farre in acts of pure Loue and Ioy, that when Friar <hi>Gregorie de Pedroſa</hi> ſaid, Now is the
<pb facs="tcp:5695:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> time to ſhew courage, hee anſwered: <hi>I neuer felt ſuch content.</hi> When his feet were tyed, hee ſaid, <hi>What doe you?</hi> The Religious told him, it was the Order. <hi>Then tye mee,</hi> ſaid hee. Comming to tye his armes, hee put them out, ſaying: <hi>Hold, tye them.</hi> Then he called the Miniſter of death (let decency excuſe me for vſing this terme) and ſaid: <hi>Come hither, Brother, let me embrace thee once more,</hi> and bowing toward him with his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, his armes being tyed, gaue him the humble kiſſe of Peace. This Act of heroick humilitie, done with deſire of greater demonſtration, drew downe many teares, either of ioy or ſorrow in the Spectators. When they tyed him in the Chaire, his Confeſſor told him, That Chriſt was alſo tyed; at which time hee remembred the Paſſion with affections burned in the fire of diuine Loue. His eyes were couered with a blacke taffata, which himſelfe had brought for that purpoſe. He lifted vp his head, ready with ioy to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme what before hee had ſo often thought of in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and ſaid, <hi>Take it, O Lord; Take it, O Lord.</hi> When the Executioner held the taffata with his left hand, to giue the ſtroke with his right hand: he forbid him, ſaying: <hi>I will ſit ſtill,</hi> with a voyce and heart ſo ſtrong, that were it lawfull, I would ſay, Naturre had priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged him from feare. Then receiued hee the ſtroke, and repeating the ſweet Name of IESVS, gaue vp his Soule. The Lookers on, though bathed in teares, beheld a ſpectacle, not horrible, but pleaſing, cauſed by a happy death. A death that hath eclipſed the greateſt examples, and limited the higheſt prayſes, whoſe duration will out-laſt the World. For were he not in Nobilitie ſo ancient, hee might hereby lay a
<pb facs="tcp:5695:10"/> foundation for a glorious Family; ſince Nobilitie is but a vertue of the mind, practized either in vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going dangers in Warre, or in giuing good examples in peace, both which were ſeene in him; and if accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the end, the vertue of the mind is to bee mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured; here onely was the loue of God, where no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect was had to the World or to Fame, which in the end will become dumbe. This example of his death hath wrought much, being in Madrid, the Court of <hi>Don Philip</hi> the Fourth, King of Spaine, where is a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall concourſe of Strangers, magnifying with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect the Spaniſh name (beſide the deſerued credit of their ancient valour) ſeeing a man paralleld with any whom the Roman cloquence did extoll, for although <hi>Sceuola, Regulus, Horatius,</hi> and many others, ſuffered much honour; yet here morally ſpeaking, it was without it. And if any were preſent at this death, either without Religion, or of a contrarie (which God forbid) what inward remorſe, vnquietneſſe of mind, and accuſation of conſcience muſt they needs haue, ſeeing ſuch ſtrange acts of Faith and Loue to God, wrought with ſuch fortitude, that it onely may teach vs the force of Truth, and Light of Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Religion. In this Glaſſe they may ſee their er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours.</p>
            <p>Thus farre my loue hath carryed mee, although my Relation bee but as a ſhaddow of this wonder: which ſuch as ſaw not, may not hope to know as it was, becauſe thoſe which were preſent, want ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacitie to declare it.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:5695:11"/>
            <p>As to the ſubſtance, I had particular information from thoſe which conuerſed with him in priſon and abroad; all Perſons of Vertue and Religion; and although I heard of much more, yet would I not inſert here but what was certayne; for a matter of it ſelfe ſo admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, needeth not borrow ornament or addition elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where.</p>
            <p>His Body lyeth buried in our Ladies Church, of the Diſcalced Carmelites in Madrid, in the Deane and Chapters Chappell. Theſe Religious, out of loue to him, buried him there, in a Tombe couered with a blacke cloth, and on it the Inſigne of his Order. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieſcant in pace.</hi> This Epitaph is written vpon his Sepulchre.
<q type="epitaph">
                  <l>He who within this Tombe doth lye,</l>
                  <l>Began to liue, when he did dye.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Soli Deo honor &amp; gloria.</q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Imprinted at Madrid with licence, by the Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of <hi>Fernando Correa de Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenegro.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:5695:11"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
